foreign
21 just a section of it
proposed that a man were to come along
carrying a a spade and a basket saying I
will make this great Earth be without
Earth he would dig here and there
scatter the soil here and there spit
here and there urinate here and there
I don't know why someone would do that
but uh be without Earth you would say be
without Earth
now what do you think would he make this
great Earth be without Earth
and they say no Lord why is that because
this Earth is immeasurable it can't
easily be made without Earth the man
would reap any disappointment
and then in the same way there are these
five aspects of speech by which Others
May address you
timely or untimely true or false
gentle or harsh
beneficial or unbeneficial with the mind
of friendliness or hate
and in that's five in any event you
should train yourselves
um our minds will not be overturned and
we will say no evil words
with a mind of friendliness without hate
we will have pity for that person we
will regard him with a friendly mind and
with that as a foundation we will regard
the whole world with a mind of
friendliness that is abundant expansive
immeasurable free from hostility
free from hostility
that's how you should train
so be be like that Earth
so I think the question was how to be
like that is the other question yeah so like
that is the other question yeah so like
the composure should be measurable to
the point where
whichever way
whoever addresses one should be the Mind
should be measurable
so just a question of you doing the
composure you do the composure that then
sets the mind up so to speak makes you
turn away from things makes it
immeasurable by things
but you don't have direct access to the
mind you can't just make it immeasurable
so that's the whole first genre practice
that we spoke before
um
mind would turn away from vitakovichara
from thinking and pondering from
movements of your thoughts from comings
and goings of your thoughts from rising
or passing away of the aggregates
by composing the context of danger
Peril lack of satisfaction
not worth my time not worth engaging all
these Myriad of aspects you can
Myriad of aspects you can
compose your mind on and then cultivate
them make sure they endure make sure you
make sure they endure make sure you
protect them through sense restraint and
virtue and the mind will have to turn
away the mind will have to lose the
interest and then you recognize that and
that's the the skill trainer and he
notices ah when I do this this is what
happens to the mind when I do that when
I compose something else or let it do
the this is what happens to the mind so
yeah as the Buddha said in that other
about the same thing be like a theory so
dwell and compose
themes contexts values of Earth of immovable
contexts values of Earth of immovable
does not is not affected by by dirt
people by spit by whatever those people
do it it just makes no difference
so by dwelling on those contexts the
mind can then
become like that
so it's indirect in a sense now the
reason why people's minds do not become
like that no matter how much work if
they dwell on the context but the minds
are not becoming like that there can
only be one reason for that minds they
themselves are still not withdrawn from
sensuality not to be drawn from
carelessness idle kind of activities talk distraction
idle kind of activities talk distraction
that keeps the Mind still connected so
to speak keeps the Mind engaged with
things that are perverting the order
so the mind is not trained it's not
developed in that sense so you can't say
oh but I'm doing everything rightly I am
fully withdrawn my virtuous impact I'm
accomplished in virtue uh accomplished
in seclusion accomplished in in
withdrawal from unwholesome States and I
can't contemplate and I compose the
context of great Earth immovability
immeasurability but my mind is still not
turning away that's impossible that's
impossible it would have to it might not
do immediately but it will have to turn
away and then you would know it
so the whole point of of the simile here
it's like yeah so make sure that your
mind is already measurable like that
Earth make sure that that context and that's
make sure that that context and that's
how you would protect the context and
see the danger of losing it like if you
just think the mind is on the level of
that context that's it but I compose
that's what it is
you will not necessarily have
perspective in regard to it which means
when you when you kind of have different
desires or want to do something
different uh the Mind might just go
ahead with it
uh but if you actually wait but this I
um this context I'm protecting now
I don't feel any danger in losing it
because I'll deal with it so to speak oh if this
I'll deal with it so to speak oh if this
context changes I'll deal with it I want
it changed or so on but that's when you
ignore how it will affect the mind for
which you don't have a say you have a
say in the context and how you compose
your mind and what you choose to dwell
on but you don't have a say in how the
mind will act and react and respond to
that and that's then your own so
although I can handle uh this context
changing and I can I can handle thinking
about different things I can handle this
I can handle this in reality I can
handle it will yeah that's not the point
the point is that the mind will do its
own thing then and you can't handle that
so you recognize the danger of losing
the context is not whether I can handle
or not new thoughts and different
thoughts the danger is oh but I know what my mind
the danger is oh but I know what my mind
will do and that's what I need to
protect so yes you can handle sensuality
great and now keep handling it keep
handling yourself away from it so that
then the mind will also not will lose
completely interest towards it
so be like Earth be like water be like
be like these elements in that in that
other sutta that's the point make your
mind become like that on account of
diligent pondering on these contexts
properties qualities that will make the
mind go that way pliable obeying that
go that way pliable obeying that
direction that you're setting up if you
have been withdrawn from sensuality
distraction uh either chatter obviously
actor Will
um and everything else pretty much oh
yes sleep uh engaging in in pointless
work distracting work and so on
then the mind will have to it will have
to turn away because you'll have to know
choice and then you realize okay so I don't
and then you realize okay so I don't
need to keep my mind now like Walter or
like like water like Earth it is so
all I need to do is not distract myself
and start providing unsuitable food for
that mind and it will stay it will stay
in regard to the entire world
so then whatever people
praise or blame
whichever they speak out of anger or
kindness it makes no difference to mind
who remains turned away from the entire
thing anyway
so yeah there's this passion because
there is no more fueling of passion
through your careless Acts
so in terms of that
that suit that other Suitor the rahula
is instructing rahula about
be like Earth and
it has the Pali word summer there so
it's like
tune into Earth
you know yeah or balance that but that's
what composure is that's what samada is
it's tuning of the context rightly
tending to it rightly and what what is
the measure of the tune
in light of what I just said what would
be the measure of oh I this is the right
tune now this passion
not being affected by what's happening
basically exactly the mind being turned away you
exactly the mind being turned away you
start recognizing that
you see that by doing that summer
rightly composing it rightly practicing
somebody rightly I establishing that
context so not on the level of abstract
ideas and certainly not from the level
of physical sensation watching
but find the balance between the two for
the lack of better word and then
got to be patient with it
and see you know you you try to tune a a
string instrument if you're just hitting
the strings and not waiting for the
feedback of the sound
how do you know whether to tighten or to
loosen so the feedback here it's is mine
so the feedback here it's is mine
turning away from the entire image from
the entire experience from thinking and
pondering and then exactly yeah this passion and
and then exactly yeah this passion and
so on that would be the result of the
Mind turn away in other words you have
then the same thoughts
they would be inducive of passion or ill
will before now the same thoughts are
there but there is no passion or ill will
but there is no passion or ill will
because the mind is not there with them
so to speak
and that's that sum aspect the the
tuning so it's not that you tune the Mind
so it's not that you tune the Mind
directly
but you tune the context appropriately
establish it make sure it endures
protect it on the basis of virtual
guiding on the sensors and the mind is
turning away
that's what that element of faith is
necessary as well in the beginning
because you don't have any immediate
feedback
and you know how you feel is certainly
not a reliable feedback oh I feel great
this must be right do I feel bad this
might be wrong not necessarily
sometimes that initial Turning Away of
the Mind might feel very unpleasant
because that's what the mind was
depending on like we draw in from the
favorite food because you don't see that
it's harming you but first you got to
stop eating it
endure that desire to eat it again and
then you realize oh actually yeah look I
am getting better
I'm lighter I'm I'm I'm I'm healthier as
a result of not eating not letting mind
sort of fall back and and touch and take
up all these other things that I used to
attend to wrongly as as
um agreeable
non-harmful and so on
because one other way of describing the
mind in in that way is that it's greater
in in that
um
I mean yeah it's broader so that
even if particular
hindrance has arise it's
in relation to those immigrants is not
not pulled by them it's able to
well yeah yeah theoretically speaking
that's correct but as I said
uh
even of itself somebody they're here to
the instruction that mind is greater
mind is broader
they can make whatever they want out of
it and that's why it's you have to like
be careful and it's like well yes you
can use these descriptions
but you need to really know why the mind
is turning away wide and it's on account
of danger
understanding the gratification danger
in the escape in regard to pretty much
anything that takes mind's interest
settle in regard to Central desire and
unwholesome states and you can
understand that if you've stopped acting
towards it if you stop distracting
yourself if you stop being sort of
threading water around and ignoring that
there is still tasks to be done all that
thing that's before so that is all part
of that development
he's not like some random observances
that they've done and then this is the
you know the the direct line to my
Enlightenment this technique or this way
of thinking or something like that
um and that's exactly why for somebody
all these things would be extremely
mystical and abstract and for somebody
would be like the most acute description
of the experience of Jannah or how the
mind turns away from centrality and so
on
the difference being in how much they've
actually developed through the body the
speech and then on the level of the
thought
so we're back to what we said before so
if if you hear an instruction it's oh
wow that sounds interesting okay then
find out more from that person or if
they said anything else says how you
arrive at it
yes there is this pleasure when the mind
is withdrawn and it's it's magical and
it's just immeasurable mind and and it's
just the absolute Bliss okay so how do I
do it
and then if they say well you know you
just sit and focus on Sensations and get
this pleasure and then latch onto it and
look closer and contemplate the nature
that's that's not really the impression
you get when you read the suitors
but if they say how did you do it well
keep the precepts be fully be drawn from
unwholesome States guard your sense
doors like your life depends on it and
then dwell in seclusion
up until your the intentions become
apparent where the Mind leans towards
pleasure leans away from pain all these
things and then you have that Bliss of
withdrawal and stuff it's like oh yeah
yeah that is when I did the sooters
that's kind of what what it says there
but everything else 99 of work leading
up to that okay yeah that's that's
covered we all understand that you know
priest said sure guarding the census
this is the way to Janna
like no because you left everything else out
no because you left everything else out
that's not the way and if somebody has
understood the way and had the Jannah
they would not be able to Omit this way
of getting there because they would
understand how they got there and you
can't stumble upon it accidentally
even the Buddha himself when he
remembered the experience of Jannah that
he had when he was still a young under
the tree there with the father somewhere
can't remember the story the point is oh
I remember that experience he obviously
knew how he got there
let me try going that way again and see
if that's the way to Enlighten it
and how you get there by by complete
withdrawal from an awesome States
mind completely turned away from
unwholesome phenomena
of last greed desire aversion
dissatisfaction five hindrances
which is different to trying to get rid
of completely different yeah see you
can't get rid of it
but you could attend to it rightly so
the Mind turns away from it while the
Thing Remains
if you're getting rid of it means you're
already your mind is already connected
with it this is no other perspective in
regard to it so you just want to replace
it because it's unbearable
no you just need to attend to it rightly
literally and that which hinders you ceases to be
and that which hinders you ceases to be
a hindrance why because the mind stand
away now the mind is not touching it
anymore it's not involved with it
anymore and trying to get rid of it is
is a very strong form of involvement
aversion
so in terms of that example you gave
about withdrawing from eating certain
types of food that were would be
unhealthy suppose suppose like you discover you
suppose suppose like you discover you
are allergic to
something that you used to find very
agreeable like in the beginning it might be
like in the beginning it might be
difficult to give up that thing that's
um you have to sort of force yourself
not to ease us
but once like you said you start to see
the benefits or see okay I am getting
healthier I don't have this discomfort
or symptoms or whatever
you kind of understand okay this is what
came of easing this unhealthy food then
it's no more really agreeable
to contemplate easing that same food
because it comes with this
implication of all of that unhealthy all
of that discomfort all of those the
symptoms of allergy or whatever
so it's like a bit similar that the
thing that used to be a source of
pleasure by having been withdrawn from it long
by having been withdrawn from it long
enough to see the kind of higher
perspective or uh
get the benefit from it to an extent now
that same thing is no more
kind of uh no more no more desirable
exactly because like okay it might taste
good but I don't want all that comes
with us yes okay tastes good it got it
basically becomes redefined as causing
illness and death and pain and
everything else so the good taste this
is to be a good taste it's just now a
harmful taste but it's like that you saw
there is still a good taste a good thing
exactly there is still that poisonous
drink factual color smell taste
everything remains unchanged but the
knowledge of poison now
can make your mind forget that can you
make mine topple over and tip over and
lose that perspective it's like that
simile as the other night of the scales
you know so you're bringing that uh that
other perception
of the danger to balance with this one
that's you know the good taste
at the same time that's the point here
not so between a danger danger replace
this replaces this remains he's that's
why I keep saying it to endure things on
the right level it remains so that you
bring the balance yeah so that you bring
the danger and leave it there count away
in it that's it
and it will have to go away and that's
why the mind will turn away from both
oh right thank you for bringing the
danger on the scale so I got that balance
on the scale so I got that balance
re-established
but without actually weighing it at the
same time
but instead trying to get rid of it
you're literally just replacing the
stuff on a scale that's already out of
the balance and that hindrance is in
acting out of hindrances oh this put it
new put a new one put a new thing put a
new thing put a new thing completely
just completely perpetuating yourself in
that turned over state
turned over state
upside down
and the reason why this peripheral
awareness that is balancing the more particular
that is balancing the more particular
hindrances is
um not evoking of craving is is because
so you can't crave towards
I mean for example the fact that the
body is yeah you find yourself in the
body inescapably or yeah the feeling is
completely out of your control these
things which are
well because craving is always always
bound with that Direction with that
particular so it's always that forward and if you
so it's always that forward and if you
establish
the scales if you start weighing the
balance through the context of the
peripheral in regard to what you're
craving craving would diminish while
That Thing Remains yeah
so that's how you uproot it you don't
replace it